Finding aid for the Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection
1920-2012
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)
8 linear feet (17 boxes)
This is collection includes information on the various buildings and properties held by Xavier University. Files may contain correspondence, brochures, newspaper clippings, dedication programs, and other types of materials.
XUA-54
Scope and Content
This collection consists of correspondence, documents, brochures, minutes of meetings, photos, diagrams and other materials pertaining to the buildings, halls, houses, centers and other properties on the Xavier campus.
The collection includes information on buildings currently in existence, some buildings that have been razed and a few proposed buildings that were never constructed. It also includes documentation concerning the closing of some streets by the City of Cincinnati in and around the campus. It does not include any of the buildings that St. Xavier College occupied in downtown Cincinnati prior to 1919. For information on the Sycamore Street buildings, consult a separate collection dealing with the Nineteenth Century St. Xavier College and Church.
In addition, this collection does not include information on any shrines, statues, monuments, fountains or permanent plaques. These materials are found in a separate collection found in the Xavier Archives.
Statement of Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by the name of the building or property.
Related Material
Other materials of related interest can be found in other collections, such as XUA-53, Xavier University Master Building Plans collection. Please contact the archives staff.
Restrictions on Access
Some parts of this collection may have restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Accruals
Additions to this collection are expected.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
College buildings--Ohio--Cincinnati; College buildings--Designs and plans
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Buildings
Detailed Description of The Collection
- Albers Hall, 1943; 1950; undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. The program for the rededication of the Hall, June 7, 1950; 2. Floor Plans of the Hall; 3. Brochures pertaining to the installation of the hall elevator.
  Albers Hall is located on the west side of the Academic Mall between Hinkle Hall and Logan Hall. It was named in honor of William H. Albers, the principal donor. Built at a cost of $244,000.00, the hall was dedicated on November 10, 1929. Originally the Biology department was found on the third floor, with the Physics and Mathematics departments on the second. Classrooms and the President's office were found on the first floor. Later the Biology department took over the entire building.
- Alter Hall, 1959-1960; undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains: 1. Announcements of the new classroom building, Alter Hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of Alter Hall; 3. Memorial possibilities in the new Alter Hall; 4. Groundbreaking (May 16, 1959); 5. Dedication Planning Committee documents; 6. Dedication ceremony (December 4, 1960).
  Alter Hall (the Alter Classroom Building) is located on the east side of the Academic Mall between Bellarmine Chapel and the McDonald Library. It was named in honor of Karl J. Alter, the Archbishop of Cincinnati. Built at a cost of $1,175,000.00, the groundbreaking ceremony took place on May 16, 1959. It was dedicated and blessed by Archbishop Alter on December 4, 1960. The facility opened for classes on February 1, 1961.
  Alter Hall originally contained 32 classrooms, Kelly Auditorium (which seated about 300) and the offices of the Deans, Academic Vice President, Registrar, Evening School, Graduate College and some departmental chairs. Classroom use closed in 2012 for extensive renovation which actually began in 2014. Reopening is planned for September, 2015.
- Alter Hall, 1961; 2010-2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. Open House inspections of the new Alter Hall; 2. Articles pertaining to the construction of Alter Hall; 3. Memos pertaining to the renovation of Alter Hall which took place between 2006 and 2014; 4. Photos and drawings of Alter Hall from the early 1960's.
- Alumni Center, 2000; 2002; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This folder contains brochures and newspaper clippings concerning the Alumni Center.
  Alumni Center is located on the south side of Dana Avenue. It was constructed as the Coca-Cola Bottling works and opened on November 28, 1938. In 1986, F&W Publications purchased the property and renovated it. The building was placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1986. In 2001, Xavier University bought the building and began another extensive renovation. As of 2014, the facility houses the Xavier Office of Physical Plant, the library annex, and a number of other offices, including University Relations.
- Armory, 1947-1948; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This folder contains correspondence, brochures, sketches and photographs concerning the Armory.
  The Armory is located on Winding Way on the West Campus. The original cost of the building was $175,000.00. The cornerstone ceremony took place on June 9, 1948, with Kenneth C. Royall, the Secretary of the United States Army, laying the cornerstone.
- Barracks Buildings, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  This folder contains one publicity item about the Barracks.
  The "Barracks" were buildings used as student housing after World War II. Ten former Army barrack buildings were brought to campus and re-erected on university property fronting on Ledgewood and Herald Avenues in October, 1946. These barracks accommodated 24 students per building (3 to a room), for a total occupancy of 240. They were razed around 1953. In addition, another barracks was erected between the University Drive and Victory Parkway. It was called North Hall and provided classroom space. Early in 1947, yet another barracks was erected opposite Alumni Science Hall (now Edgecliff Hall), near the entrance to the University Drive. It was called South Hall and served as a snack bar and a theater. Both North Hall and South Hall have been subsequently razed.
- Bellarmine Chapel, 1930-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Correspondence, newspaper articles, and a history of the Chapel; 2. Directories and Family Quick Listings of Chapel members.
  St. Robert Bellarmine Chapel was canonically established as a parish by John T. McNicholas, the Archbishop of Cincinnati, in 1927. It was located on the first floor of the Schmidt Library building and served as both a student chapel and archdiocesan parish. The "new" Bellarmine Chapel was dedicated and blessed by Karl J. Alter, Archbishop of Cincinnati, on December 16, 1962. The chapel is named in honor of St. Robert Bellarmine, Jesuit theologian and saint. The new chapel also honors the memory of Charles F. and Elizabeth Williams whose five children were the principal donors. The original cost of the "new" chapel was $364,000.00.
- Bellarmine Chapel, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  This folder contains materials on: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony of the "new" chapel, (May 13, 1961); 2. Laying of the cornerstone of the "new" chapel (September 26, 1962); 3. Dedication of the chapel (December 16, 1962).
- Bellarmine Chapel, 1961-2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  This folder contains materials on: 1. Dedication of the St. Robert Bellarmine statue (June 15, 1969); 2. Rededication of the chapel (September 13, 1998); 3. Bellarmine Chapel annual "Steward Reports;" 4. Photos and brochures.
- Boylan Hall, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  This folder contains limited correspondence concerning Boylan Hall.
  Boylan Hall was originally a family residence on Ledgewood Avenue next to Bellarmine Chapel. Purchased by the university, it was named in honor of the Rev. Murtha Boylan, S.J., professor of psychology for many years. In the 1960s it housed the office of the Assistant to the President as well as faculty offices. In the early 1970s it served as the Undergraduate Recruitment and Admission Office. It was razed in the late 1970s to make room for Hailstones Hall.
- Breen Lodge, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  This folder contains notes concerning the history of Breen Lodge written by the Xavier Archives staff.
  Breen Lodge, located on Ledgewood Drive across from Brockman Hall, was originally a residential house used by Xavier Jesuits. Subsequently it was used by various campus groups including its use as a women's center at Xavier. It was probably named to honor the Rev. Aloysius A. Breen, S.J., who was the treasurer of Xavier University at one time.
- Brockman Hall, 1950-1954; undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  This folder contains: 1. A brochure announcing the construction of Brockman Hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction and naming of Brockman Hall; 3. A brochure about gift opportunities.
  This building was named in honor of the Rev. Hubert F. Brockman, S.J., president of Xavier from 1923 to 1931. The original cost of the building was $915,000.00. Groundbreaking took place on May 16, 1953. Its dedication and blessing occurred on May 21, 1955. Myers Y. Cooper, former Governor of Ohio, eulogized Fr. Brockman on this occasion.The dedication of the St. Francis Xavier mural in the Brockman Hall lounge happened on May 18, 1957. The dedication of the Mackentepe Memorial Lounge was on June 9, 1959.
- Brockman Hall, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  This folder contains information on the following: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony; 2. Dedication and blessing ceremony; 3. Dedication of the St. Francis Xavier mural; 4. Dedication of the Mackentepe Memorial Lounge.
- Brockman Hall, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  This folder contains information about a proposed, but never built, swimming pool for Brockman Hall.
- Cintas Center, 1993-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  This folder contains brochures about the Convocation Center (later called the Cintas Center) and some Convocation Center planning documents.
  The Cintas is Xavier University's athletic facility. In addition to providing the basketball arena for the university team, this building houses the Athletic Department and other campus offices.
- Cintas Center, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  This folder contains memos, meeting notes, and other items concerning the planning of the Convocation Center.
- Cintas Center, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  This folder contains the document "Site Specific Health and Safety Plan: The Cintas Center, Xavier University....Prepared for Xavier University, May 8, 1998." Other materials are included.
  Some materials may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.
- Cintas Center, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  This folder contains memorandums, contractor lists and the commemorative section by Cincinnati Magazine entitled "Cintas Center: a View Inside the Spectacular Cintas Center at Xavier University."
- Cintas Center, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  This folder contains information on the relationship of Xavier University to the City of Norwood about the Cintas Center.
- Cintas Center, 2001-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  This folder contains marketing brochures, a catering guide, testimonial letters and other items about the Cintas Center.
- Cintas Center, 1997-2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  This folder contains newspaper articles about the Cintas Center.
- Cintas Center, 2001-2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  This folder contains overview information about the Cintas Center. Also included is the document "Cintas Center: the First Five Years."
- Cohen Center, 1978-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  This folder includes a Cohen Center fact sheet as well as correspondence.
  The A.B. Cohen Center was formerly the 18 acre Norwood facility of the U.S. Shoe Corporation on Cleneay Avenue. It was gifted to Xavier University in November, 1978. In 1987, after extensive renovation, the Center became the home of the Departments of Art, Nursing, and Hospital and Health Administration.
- Cohen Center, 1978; 1980; undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  This folder contains a 1978 U.S. Shoe Annual Report and also documents concerning a 1980 lawsuit concerning the U.S. Shoe property.
  This folder may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.
- Cohen Center, 1979; undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  This folder contains documents relating to the 1980 lawsuit involving the Cohen property.
- Conaton Learning Commons, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  This folder contains some brochures about the Conaton Learning Commons and the speakers program for the grand opening of the facility.
  For more information on the construction of this building, consult XUA-53, the Xavier University Master Building Plans collection.
  The Conaton Learning Commons was named to honor Michael J. Conaton, Class of 1955, chair of the Xavier Board of Trustees (1985-2004), and one-time acting president. The naming was at the request of Charles P. Gallagher, 1960 graduate. Mr. Gallagher's generous gift helped to build this state of the art facility. The Conaton Learning Commons is part of the James E. Hoff, S.J. Academic Quadrangle project. It opened on July 20, 2010.
- Corcoran Football Field, 1927-1968 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  This folder contains correspondence, blueprints and some news clippings pertaining to this facility.
  The west side of the field, with a seating capacity of 3,750, was completed and dedicated on October 22, 1921. The east side was completed and dedicated on November 23, 1929. This addition increased the seating capacity to about 15,000. The field was razed in 1988 and was replaced by the soccer field that is presently there.
- Edgecliff Hall [Formerly Alumni Science Hall], 1920-1962; 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  This folder contains information on: 1. Geoghegan Language Laboratory; 2. Renovation and renaming.
  Completed and opened for classes in September, 1920, it was the first building constructed by St. Xavier College on its new Avondale campus. It was a gift from the alumni who contributed to the Diamond Jubilee Fund of St. Xavier College in 1915. After extensive renovation, it was rededicated in April, 2000, and renamed Edgecliff Hall to honor the former Edgecliff College and its graduates. The original cost of the building was $188,000.00.
- Elet Hall, 1927-1988; undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  This folder contains various materials pertaining to Elet Hall, chiefly regulations for student conduct in this facility.
  Elet Hall is located on Winding Way on the West Campus. It was built as a dormitory which accommodated about 100 students. The formal opening took place on October 4, 1924. With its opening Xavier once again became a "boarding institution." The building was named after Xavier's first Jesuit president, John A. Elet, S.J.. The original cost of the building was $ 249,000.00.
- Fenwick Place [also known as Bishop Fenwick Place], 2009-2011; undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  This folder contains sundry documents concerning this property. Included are brochures, a ground blessing program, a news release, and other materials.
  This building is named in honor of Bishop Edward Dominic Fenwick, O.P., the first bishop of Cincinnati and founder of the Athenaeum, as Xavier University was originally called. The dining room within this building is named in honor of Father James E. Hoff, the president of Xavier from 1991 to 2000. The ground blessing took place on May 7, 2010. The building opened in August, 2011. The building is home to student residences and the offices of the Bursar, Registrar, Mission and Identity, among others.
- Flynn Hall, 1991 August 14 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  This folder contains the dedication program for the Center (dated August 14, 1991).
  This building was originally named the Lawrence J. Flynn, S.J. Broadcast Center. Its original address was 1648 Herald Avenue, but was changed to 1648 Musketeer Drive. The building was named to honor the Rev. Lawrence J. Flynn, S.J., founder of Xavier radio, and was dedicated on August 14, 1991. The building was originally part of the U.S. Shoe Corporation property which was donated to Xavier in 1978. It was home to the Xavier radio station, WVXU-FM, from approximately 1991 to 2005. Xavier sold WVXU in March, 2005. Sometime after 2005, the Center became an office building housing several Xavier services including the campus police.
- Gallagher Student Center, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  This folder contains various brochures and the script of the dedication ceremony of the building.
  The Gallagher Student Center is located at the juncture of the Academic Mall and the Residential Mall, across from Bellarmine Chapel. It is named in honor of Charles P. Gallagher, Class of 1960, the principal donor. The building's original cost was $ 13,955,000.00. The building contains a theatre, bookstore, conference rooms, offices, a food court and shops. It replaced the University Center Building which stood on the same site. It was dedicated and opened in 2002.
- Hailstones Hall, 1976-1985; undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Timeline of the building's construction and description of the hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of the hall; 3. Groundbreaking Ceremony (November 29, 1979); 4. Dedication of the hall (April 30, 1981); 5. The addition of a third floor to the hall; 6. Photo of the hall.
  Hailstones Hall (formerly called the College of Business Administration Building) was named in honor of Dr. Thomas J. Hailstones, founder and first dean of the College of Business Administration (now known as the Williams College of Business). Groundbreaking took place on November 29, 1979 and the dedication occurred on April 30, 1981. A third floor was added several years later. The original cost of the building was approximately $4,300,000.00.
  In 2010, the Williams College of Business moved to the newly constructed Stephen and Dolores Smith Hall. Then the College of Social Sciences, Education and Health moved into Hailstones Hall.
- Hailstones Hall Correspondence and Programs, 1979-1985 (Box 6, Folder 1A)
- Herald Avenue (Closing of), 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  This folder consists chiefly of correspondence concerning the closure of Herald Avenue and transfer of the property to Xavier University.
  On May 7, 1958 the City of Cincinnati vacated Herald Avenue from Dana Avenue to Ledgewood Avenue and sold the property to Xavier University. Xavier renamed the street the "Academic Mall."
- Hinkle Hall, 1953-1957; undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  This folder contains: 1. Documents pertaining to the two statues on the exterior of the Hall; 2. 1957 prank: Hinkle Hall for sale; 3. Floor plans of the Hall before and after the departure of the Jesuit Community in 1970; 4.Photos of the Hall and O'Brien Terrace.
  Hinkle Hall is located on the Academic Mall between Schmidt Hall and Albers Biology Hall. It was named in honor of Mrs. Frederick Wallis Hinkle, the principal donor. Built at an original cost of $ 256,000.00, it was completed in 1920. It served as the residence of the Jesuit community from 1920 to 1970, after which the Jesuits moved to Schott Hall. It became a faculty office building in 1970.
- Hinkle Hall, 1970-1974 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  This folder contains materials pertaining to the renovation of the Hall after the Jesuit Community moved its residence to Schott Hall in early February, 1970.
- Husman Hall, 1963-1990 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  This folder contains: 1. Correspondence concerning the construction of the Hall; 2. Dedication and blessing of the Hall (November 28, 1965); 3. Floor plans, photos and drawings of the Hall.
  Husman Hall is a student residence hall. It was named in honor of Harry J. Husman, the principal donor. Built at an original cost of $ 793,000.00, it was blessed and dedicated on November 28, 1965.
- Husman Hall, 1959-1966; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President (Box 7, Folder 2)
  This folder contains documents on the mortgage of Husman Hall. These documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the Executive Vice President of Xavier University.
- Husman Hall, 1969-1981; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President (Box 7, Folder 3)
  Mortgage documents related to Husman Hall. These documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the Executive Vice President of Xavier University.
- Husman Hall, 1964-1966; undated; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President (Box 7, Folder 4)
  This folder contains mortgage documents related to Husman Hall. These documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the Executive Vice President of Xavier University.
- Joseph Building, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  This folder includes information about the building, correspondence, dedication brochures, and photos.
  The George J. Joseph Building, housing the Center for Human Development, is located on Dana Avenue near Winding Way. It stands on the site of the old Avondale Athletic Club which became the Xavier Union Building when Xavier purchased the property in the early 1900s. The Joseph Building was built at a cost of $ 450,000.00. It was dedicated on December 1, 1968.
- Kuhlman Hall, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  This folder contains information on: 1. Naming of Kuhlman Hall; 2. Dedication of Kuhlman Hall; 3. Photos of Kuhlman Hall; 4. Correspondence about the creation of the James F. Griffin, III, Recreation Lounge; 5. Dedication of the James F. Griffin Recreation Lounge.
  Kuhlman Hall was named in honor of George H. and Rose Kuhlman, parents of Leo G., Kuhlman (Class of 1911) and Lawrence B. Kuhlman (Class of 1914). Built at a cost of $ 1,800,000.00, it was dedicated and blessed on December 10, 1967. It accommodated 432 students. The dedication of the James F. Griffin III Recreation Lounge within Kuhlman Hall occurred on May 5, 1968.
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, 1992-1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 8, Folder 1)
  This folder contains correspondence, minutes, blueprints, and other materials relating to the proposed development of Ledgewood Avenue into a cul-de-sac incorporated into part of the Xavier campus. This folder originally came from files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
  This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, Supplement 1, 1992-1993; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 8, Folder 2)
  This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book One's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.
  This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, Supplement 2, 1992-1993; undated; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, Supplement 3, 1993 August 14; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President (Box 8, Folder 4)
  This folder contains materials found loose within Book One's large three-ring binder. This is a Cincinnati Herald newspaper of August 14, 1993 containing the headline "XU and City Council Close Ledgewood Drive." This folder originally came from files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.